<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A visitation in love to those of the people called Baptists, with whom the Lords Spirit yet ceaseth not to strive, that have not slain the witness by making war, and contending against the light ... by one who travels in the Spirit for their souls good ... J.A.</title>
            <author>Anderdon, John, 1624?-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13413717</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13413717</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99439</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25352)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99439)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 782:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A visitation in love to those of the people called Baptists, with whom the Lords Spirit yet ceaseth not to strive, that have not slain the witness by making war, and contending against the light ... by one who travels in the Spirit for their souls good ... J.A.</title>
                  <author>Anderdon, John, 1624?-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: John Anderdon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99439:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99439:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Viſitation in Love To thoſe of the People called BAPTISTS, with whom the Lords Spirit yet ceaſeth not to ſtrive, that have not ſlain the Witneſs, by making War, and contending againſt the Light, who although they may think themſelves Rich, and increaſed with much goods, yet are found to be Wretched and Miſerable, Poor, and Blind, and Naked.</p>
            <p>With Councel from the Lord, that they without delay (before a farther day of Miſery and Calamity overtake them) come away from all blind Leaders, and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Teachers (who keep them alwayes learning, but never bring them to the knowledge of the Truth) unto the ſpirit of the living God, the everlaſting Teacher of his People, that ſo they may ceaſe from all their own works and labours, and ſtand ſtill, and wait to know and feel the Lords work wrought in them, by the Arm of Gods Salvation, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> of the world, <hi>the only way</hi> to the Father.</p>
            <p>That they may no longer feed on words, and ſeek after that food that periſheth, But that they may all come to feed on the Word of Life, on that Bread which came down from God out of Heaven; That they may know the fountain of Life ſet open in themſelves, that out of their bellies may flow forth rivers of living Waters, to the refreſhment of their immortal Souls, and the Heritage of God.</p>
            <p>By one who travels in Spirit for their Souls good, and by the everlaſting Light of the Son of God is come to ſee and know, that though <hi>Johns</hi> Miniſtration once committed to him in its time was Excellent and Glorious, and he the greateſt born of a woman, yet a greater than <hi>John</hi> is come; and that the leaſt in the Kingdome is greater than <hi>John, J. A.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon</hi> at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Wind-mil</hi> in <hi>Martins le Grand,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:99439:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99439:2"/>
            <head>IN LO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Viſitation to thoſe of the People called <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> with whom the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit yet ceaſeth not to ſtrive, that have not ſlain the Witneſſe by making War, and Contending againſt the Light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Truly Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving wandred in times paſt from Mountaine to Hill to find paſture and refreſhment for my ſoul which is immortal, and will not be ſatisfied but with that Food which Periſheth not, when it was the earneſt deſire of my very heart to be delivered from the bondage of corruption, and to be brought into the Liberty of the Sons of God, (for which the whole Creation groans) daily panting and breathing after the waters of life, that in the living Truth of God I might be ſet free to ſerve the living God: And in this, though my deſires were pure, yet I labouring for the accompliſhment thereof in <hi>my</hi> own ſtrength and way in all my performances and duties (as I judged) in imitation of what others hath done and performed in dayes of old, and months paſt in the Power of Gods Spirit: But I being not in, and guided by the ſame ſpirit, all my <hi>labour</hi> was in <hi>vain, it being not in the Lord,</hi> though in never ſo like imitation from the Letter of Scriptures, wherein I ſtrove long to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome, but in vain is ſalvation expected from the Hills, or from the Mountains, but from <hi>him</hi> who is mighty to ſave, the Arme of Gods Salvation, <hi>the Word of God which is nigh
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99439:3"/>in the heart and in the mouth, In him alone I found everlaſting ſtrength,</hi> which giveth Victory and Dominion over ſin and corruption, which lodgeth in the heart of every man by nature, wherein he is a child of wrath: Out of which eſtate, I verily believe, it is the deſire of many ſouls amongſt you to know Gods Salvation and Redemption, and that you might yet at length, after <hi>a cloudy and dark day</hi> which hath been <hi>over you,</hi> come forth to the new and <hi>living way,</hi> to the glorious <hi>Light</hi> of the Goſpel, which is <hi>the Power of God unto Salvation,</hi> that you henceforth might <hi>ſerve him</hi> no longer in the oldneſſe of the Letter, but in the newneſſe of the Spirit, which is only accepted by the Lord, In whom my ſoul hath often travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and ſeriouſly weighed your condition of Bondage, under ſuch Elements as muſt paſſe away, and be conſumed with the Spirit of burning, which muſt paſſe upon all fleſh that ſhall be ſaved.</p>
            <p>Verily, touching you, I have had often thoughts of heart, who ſometime were a people, that in a meaſure, and in ſome things did run well; but who hath bewitched you (I may ſay) that begun in the Spirit, that now ye ſhould think to be made perfect in the fleſh, in which ye will certainly end, unleſs you come in every particular <hi>to be witneſſes in your ſelves of the new Birth,</hi> in the new and living way, <hi>Chriſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you the hope of Glory?</hi> And all your Ordinances, as you call them, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, ſhall not cover you, nor ſtand you in ſtead in the day of the Lord, when nothing but the covering of the Lords Spirit ſhall hide you from the wrath of the Lamb; Truly Friends, my bowells yearn towards you, knowing that there is <hi>a right Seed</hi> in ſome of you that groans to come forth out of the priſon, from under the bonds of the cruel Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor, the enemy of your immortal ſoules, Oh! that you would yet at length learn to be wiſe unto Salvation, and no longer lay out your money for that which is no bread, but that you might all come to him, who is the <hi>way,</hi> the <hi>truth,</hi> and the <hi>life, Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>light</hi> of the world, through the Croſs to the Crown, from things that fade and periſh even with the uſe thereof, unto that which is everlaſting, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall fade away.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99439:3"/>
            <p>Verily I have felt, and born the burden of <hi>your Apoſtacy,</hi> which hath grieved the good Spirit of our God, that on the 14th day of the tenth month, 1659. in the time of the late revolutions, as I was paſſing on my way towards <hi>London,</hi> this was the Lords complaint touching you, in theſe words, <hi>They have betrayed me into the hands of Sinners,</hi> when you had a day, time and opportunity put in your hands to do ſervice for the Lord, but you like fools had not hearts to make uſe of it; And I know that <hi>you are not in the way that ſhall proſper,</hi> neither are your Sacrifices or ſervices accepted by the Lord, you being gone back from that pure principle that ſometime called you to repentance, and to come out of the world; and are gone after your own inventions, and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations from the <hi>Letter,</hi> which killeth, and come not to the <hi>Spirit</hi> which <hi>giveth life:</hi> You cannot chuſe but confeſſe, that, that ſavour that ſometimes you might be ſenſible to be in your ſervices, is gone from you, and <hi>what meaneth your ſtay any longer in that place or thing where God is not to be found?</hi> And of this be aſſured, the more you ſtrive in your vaine minds to build up that which God pluck down and diſownes, the farther you go from the way of reſt and peace, and <hi>unleſs you repent, and return, you ſhall lye down in ſorrow;</hi> yea, the higheſt and talleſt Cedar amongſt you ſhall know that the Lord God is confounding the wiſdom of the wiſe, and all the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and <hi>Images</hi> ſet up, or practiced by men in their inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and fallen wiſdom is but <hi>abomination</hi> in the ſight of the Lord, though in your ſervices you could ſpeak even with the Tongue of men and Angells, yet you being not in the right <hi>Spirit,</hi> you find not acceptance with God, but are <hi>barren</hi> and <hi>unfruitful</hi> unto God in all that you do; And if you <hi>ſtand ſtil,</hi> me thinks you cannot chuſe but ſee from whence ye are fallen, how low, weak and carnall all your perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances are, <hi>imagining</hi> to your ſelves <hi>a life in things</hi> that are <hi>dead,</hi> and will not come to him who hath the words of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, who was before <hi>Abraham,</hi> was to that <hi>word</hi> which was in the beginning, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus the Light</hi> of the world, the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever; <hi>He that was dead is a live, and behold he liveth for evermore,</hi> unto whom you muſt all come
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99439:4"/>for Salvation, as he is come a <hi>Light</hi> into the world, there being Salvation in no other name under Heaven, and this is the <hi>mighty Power of God unto Salvation;</hi> and whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in him ſhall not periſh, but have <hi>Eternal Life:</hi> And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ye come unto the <hi>Light,</hi> and follow it, you ſhall for ever abide in darkneſſe; and though it ſeem never ſo ſmall and contemptible a thing in your eyes (but <hi>as a grain of muſtard ſeed</hi>) by reaſon of your high profeſſion, which ſometimes hath had eſteem amongſt men; yet unto it you muſt all bow and yeild obedience, if ever you expect Salvation to your immortal Souls, there being not <hi>another way</hi> but this which will bring you down, and teach you to become fools, and deny your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, and to take up the daily Croſs to the carnal mind, that by it, which is the power of God, you may witneſſe a death unto ſin, even in the root and ground from whence all the works of darkneſſe doe proceed.</p>
            <p>This Light is the mavellous <hi>Light</hi> which <hi>will ſhew you all things</hi> that you have done, and will lead you in the path of life. And truly Friends, to me it is a thing to be Lamented, that you, a profeſſing people, that have ſeemed ſo zealous for the way of the Lord, as that you ſhould now be ſo blind as to hate the Light, and not to come to it, to try the power and ſtrength thereof, what it will do for you at length, after all your own Labours, from which you muſt ceaſe, and in the <hi>ſilence of all fleſh</hi> (which is a <hi>hard work</hi>) waite to hear the voice of the true Shepheard, which will teach you to do the will of God. Surely this I conclude, that if you come not to the <hi>Light,</hi> it is becauſe your deeds are evil; for it <hi>makes</hi> all things <hi>manifeſt,</hi> even the hidden things of the heart, &amp; brings the ſinner to judgment, through which <hi>Sions</hi> redemption is to be known; what think ye friends, that its dangerous to come to that <hi>Principle of</hi> God, which teacheth to deny ungodlineſſe, and worldly luſts, and to walk righteouſly, ſoberly, and godly, in this preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill world? which is the <hi>grace of God,</hi> that bringeth ſalvation, which hath appeared unto all men, that <hi>light</hi> which enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth every man that cometh into world, that <hi>Spirit</hi> which <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth the world</hi> of ſin, and <hi>leadeth us</hi> into all truth, is he that we teſtify of, and perſwade all men every where to <hi>take heed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99439:4"/>unto, and follow.</hi> And are you affraid of him, and do you look for another, becauſe his Viſage is marred more than any? and do you fly the croſſe, becauſe of the ſhame? onelſe what is it, that makes you ſtand at ſuch a diſtance from the way of life? know yee not that the Kingdome is for the poor and hungry, and that the fat and ſtrong are for judgement, and the rich are ſent empty away? Truely friends, if that pure principle of God that ſomtimes breathed in you after Gods righteouſneſs, be ſo choaked and ſtifled in you, through the deceitfulneſs of ſin, and the cares of this life, with <hi>things</hi> that are <hi>carnall,</hi> which <hi>feeds not</hi> the <hi>birth immortall,</hi> that it ceaſeth to ſtrive and ſtir in you, your caſe is lamentable, you are but clouds without water, carryed about of winds, trees whoſe fruit withe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth; yea without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots, the end whereof is for the fire of Gods wrath in the day of the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his righteous judgements upon the workers of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in which you are found <hi>without the Spirit of life and power,</hi> under the deepeſt coverings of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> wherein the <hi>myſtery of iniquity</hi> lodgeth in thoſe dayes of his reigne in the hearts of the children of diſobedience, even <hi>in the higheſt likeneſſes of words,</hi> and conformity to the letter, that he is even transformed into an Angell of Light to deceive many, who comes not to the <hi>light of life and power of God,</hi> which <hi>diſcovers and deſtroyes his Kingdome, root and branch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What aileth you? is blindneſſe happened unto you, that you cannot ſee where you are? and that it ſhall be <hi>more tollerable for Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah</hi> in the day of judgement <hi>than for theſe</hi> that are called Jews, but are not, <hi>that have a name that they live, but are dead</hi> in ſins and treſpaſſes; ſee you not, how through your deceit, hypocriſie, and <hi>unfaithfulneſſe to Gods witneſſe</hi> in you, you have <hi>brought up your enemies</hi> on top of you, that miſery threatens your perſons, &amp; barrenneſs &amp; leanneſs is entred into your very ſouls? ſo that fear, the pit, and the ſnare, daily attends you, that you are become weak and unſtable as water, that ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that you have ſo much builded upon, and are become a ſhame unto Religion by your abominable <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from the wayes of truth, and the paths of righteouſneſſe, unto which you have ſometimes had a Call, and a Day to make it manifeſt,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99439:5"/>but you would not come down to the fooliſhneſſe of the Croſs of Chriſt, that ſo in him yee might have been more than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors over all your enemyes, within and without; but have choſen your own wayes, and <hi>ſet up the abomination which mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth deſolate,</hi> and ſtandeth in the place where it ought not, and have made that which ſhould be the Temple of the living God, a Cage of unclean Birds; the enemy having found the houſe as it were ſwept and garniſhed, is returned again with ſeven worſe Spirits than himſelf, oppoſing the living truth of our God, and that under a profeſſion of God, and of Chriſt, of the Scriptures, of Ordinances, of the Words of the Prophets and Apoſtles, yet hating, envying, reproaching, and perſecuting them that live the life of the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, that in ſincerity and godly ſimplicity <hi>ſerve the Lord God in the meaſure of his eternall Spirit,</hi> which to you may ſeem a low thing that <hi>can pray when you will, and preach when you will,</hi> that have made ſuch a great ſhew <hi>in the fleſh,</hi> in that wiſdome which comprehends not the things of God whereby yee have gained (it may be) <hi>praiſe of men,</hi> the which you would fain keep up <hi>above the Croſſe of Chriſt.</hi> But down you muſt bring all your glory and excellency under the feet of the Lamb, if ever you expect to be crowned with him in glory everlaſting in that <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which is not of this world, that conſiſts not in meates and drinks, not in words, but <hi>in power,</hi> in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Peace, and Joy in the holy Ghoſt, <hi>unto which the Light will ſhew you the onely way,</hi> which ſhineth in the <hi>darkneſſe</hi> which is <hi>in the heart</hi> of man, &amp; gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth us the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt. What think you of your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Diſputations, and <hi>literall knowledge</hi> of the way of truth, and the way of life? what ſins doth it give you victory over? and what ſtands it you inſtead in the day of tryall? is not all the excellency and glory thereof but a <hi>barren empty thing</hi> that refreſheth not, nor comforteth your immortal ſoules, which onely with that bread of life which came down out of heaven are ſatisfied? Try your ſelves; have you that <hi>Life</hi> in you, which is to be <hi>felt and handled</hi> in the preſence of the Lord? or elſe it is but a thing in <hi>notion</hi> that you feed upon, which <hi>ſtarves your ſoules?</hi> I know you cannot but be ſenſible
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99439:5"/>that you have loſt that in your ſelves which ſometime in a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, gave you the ſence and ſavour of the things of God in the dayes of your infancy, when the Lord was plucking down the loſtineſſe of man, before you went about to ſet up a <hi>build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> after your own inventions and imaginations which will come to nothing. It being <hi>not upon the Rock</hi> of Ages, the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many Generations, as moved and directed thereunto by his eternall Spirit: And now I believe, as you deale faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and honeſtly with your own hearts, you cannot but ſee and confeſſe, that by all <hi>your hard labour, ſtudy, and performances of duties</hi> (as you may call them) from the letter of Scriptures, and uſe of your ordinances, you <hi>cannot again recover that which you have loſt of the ſavour of life,</hi> but grow dead, yea wax worſe and worſe, though it may be more frequent in your ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces than ever; you cry, but God hears you not, neither doth he regard the <hi>work</hi> of <hi>your</hi> hands which are <hi>abominable</hi> in his ſight, your <hi>ſacrifices</hi> being not offered up in <hi>Abels</hi> nature, <hi>from the new birth, find</hi> not <hi>acceptance with God;</hi> but are wholly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterated from the preſent teachings of his Spirit, as if the Scriptures were given forth to ſtop his mouth for ever; ſo that you have loſt your judgements and underſtanding in the things of God, and know not the voyce of the true Shepheard from a Hireling, a Wolf that comes to you in ſheeps cloathing; and <hi>ſhall never come againe to find that which you have loſt, nor to the knowledge of God and of Chriſt,</hi> whom to know is <hi>eternall-life; but as you come out of all your own wayes, wills, and worſhips unto the</hi> everlaſting <hi>Light</hi> of the Son of God <hi>in your ſelves,</hi> which will ſhew you the way to the Father, and let you ſee how far wide you are of the ſtraight and narrow way that leadeth unto the Kingdome of God, unto that pure principle of God that will ſhew you all that ever yee have done muſt you be reduced, which will bring you to the beginning of Gods Creation, that the ſtate of a little child you may come to know, waiting in the filence of fleſh to hear the Fathers voyce, which will lead you to do his will in every particular, <hi>that no longer, your own wills, but the will of God, may be done</hi> in earth as it is in heaven, that <hi>righteouſneſſe and truth</hi> may be made manifeſt in your mortall bodies, which is <hi>Chriſt in us, the hope of glory,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99439:6"/>who is come to do the will of the Father in us: And <hi>this is he</hi> that we have waited for, and we know him to be <hi>our Saviour,</hi> becauſe he <hi>ſaveth us from our ſins,</hi> and not becauſe he told the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> all that ever ſhe had done, do we believe; but becauſe his wonderfull <hi>works done in us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare him to be the Son of God,</hi> whoſe manifeſtation is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the work of the Devill in the Creature, and ſo ſet him free in Soul, Body and Spirit to ſerve the Lord God of the Spirits of all fleſh.</p>
            <p>Come down from ſelfe-conceitedneſſe, and all the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines that you have ſet up, and account it not much to be aſhamed of all your hope, which is but dead, and to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count all as dung and droſſe that you may</hi> yet at length <hi>win Chriſt, whoſe love is better than wine,</hi> and though the world hates and ſcornes him, yet he is the <hi>faireſt of ten thouſands,</hi> and <hi>unto his Light in you muſt yee be turned</hi> from the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if ever you expect to ſee his appearance, and behold his glory to the comfort of your ſoules, who is now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalvation? what will it profit you to talk of his Reign and come not to the Kingdome wherein his power, and glory is revealed, that <hi>in the heart</hi> where Satans ſeat hath been, you may <hi>witneſſe</hi> all his and <hi>your ſoules enemies ſubdued and deſtroyed,</hi> that you may know the Kingdoms come whereof Chriſt Jeſus is the King, and Law-giver, unto whom the Father hath given all Power and Authority in heaven and earth, unto whom all principalities and powers muſt how: Stand no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger about needles queſtions, but come to <hi>know Gods work wrought in your ſelves,</hi> that the heir of life may be brought forth, that your ſoules may inherit ſubſtance, that you may eat his <hi>fleſh</hi> and drink his <hi>blood,</hi> and be guided by his <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> who is the Son of God for ever, that your ſouls may be ſatisfied that <hi>this is the man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> whom ye have waited for, and that you may ſee his ſalvation, and ſay that <hi>this is he,</hi> and that you look not for another, of whoſe Power, Kingdom and glory there ſhall be no end.</p>
            <p>And now friends, to you that yet retain ſome integrity, and have longing deſires after the way of Gods ſalvation, <hi>its the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99439:6"/>Lords Councell that you delay not but come away</hi> from all your blind guides and leaders which cauſe you to erre, and wait upon the Lord <hi>to know the teachings of his pure Spirit,</hi> which will bring you to the endleſſe <hi>Fountain of life,</hi> and to feed on that bread which will nouriſh your ſoules up unto everlaſting life, and <hi>dwell no longer in the tents of the wicked,</hi> though never ſo fairly covered, <hi>leaſt your Talents be alſo taken from you, and given to others:</hi> And believe it, it is far better to ſuffer perſecution with the people of the Lord for righteouſneſſe ſake, than to enjoy the pleaſures of <hi>ſin</hi> in this world for a ſeaſon, which <hi>will end in ſorrow;</hi> and do not reject the light, and make war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods witneſſe, <hi>as ſome have done, and periſhed in their gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying,</hi> leaſt you be alſo cut off from the Land of the living, and the day of your viſitation paſſe over your heads; But <hi>come to the light that you may ſee to work</hi> out your ſalvation with fear and trembling while it is called to day, for the night cometh wherein none can work. Therefore prize your time, for the Lord wil cut ſhort the work in Righteouſneſſe for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects ſake, and be ye ſeparate, and come out from amongſt the unfruitfull workers of darkneſſe, that you may learn to walk in the way to ever laſting life, in which it is the very deſire of my ſoul to meet you, even in <hi>the way of Gods ſalvation,</hi> which is but <hi>one,</hi> through the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of <hi>one Spirit</hi> into <hi>one Body,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>the head;</hi> and ſtrive no longer about words and formes, but <hi>come to</hi> him, who is <hi>the word of life,</hi> that you may be brought from under Satans power into the power of God, and in him live, dwell, and abide for ever, that you may no more goe down again into <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> to feed on the <hi>fleſh-pots</hi> thereof, which will but <hi>make leane your ſoules,</hi> and fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten you for the day of ſlaughter which is haſtening upon the wicked. And let not the faire and feigned words of ſome (that even make merchandize of your ſoules) any longer deceive you with the <hi>enticing words of mans wiſdome</hi> to <hi>keep</hi> you <hi>in bondage,</hi> but come to the <hi>Light</hi> in your own particulars, that you may feele the <hi>Life,</hi> without which you are dead, and all your ſervices are but abomination in the ſight of the Lord, who is the living
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99439:7"/>God, and the dead praiſe him not: <hi>Seeke no longer for the living amongſt the dead;</hi> but to the <hi>Light,</hi> to the <hi>Law written in the heart,</hi> to the <hi>Teſtimony of Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Spirit of propheſie,</hi> that you may witneſſe the <hi>true annointing</hi> in your ſelves, which will teach you all things, that you may not be <hi>fooliſh</hi> Virgins without oyle in your Lamps, and ſo ſhut out of Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in which ſtate the <hi>higheſt profeſſors</hi> of the letter are, <hi>that witneſſe not the Life and Power in themſelves.</hi> Therefore redeem the time becauſe the dayes are evill, and cleave no longer to lying vanities, and forſake your own mercies, but repent, and return to the Lord God, withall your hearts, withall your mindes, and withall your ſoules, that you may <hi>live</hi> for ever <hi>in the Lambs Light of life,</hi> in which the Nations of them that are ſaved ſhall walk.</p>
            <p>And ſit down and conſider whereunto have your teachers brought you in ſo many years, but even into trouble and diſſatisfaction, not knowing whether to goe for reſt to <hi>your pretious ſoules,</hi> which are even <hi>languiſhing under deaths power,</hi> and ſhall not find refreſhment but <hi>in the preſence of the Lord,</hi> unto which <hi>the Light onely will bring you.</hi> See you not how dead and dull your teachers are become, ſtriving to keep you in that which profits you not, but ſtarves your ſoules? and how nigh they are come to be one with the hirelings, who form wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons from the Scriptures to fight againſt the Lord of life, pleading againſt <hi>perfection</hi> in this life, becauſe <hi>they cannot attain</hi> thereunto <hi>in their way;</hi> laying <hi>hold on the ſins of others, that they themſelves may continue ſinners:</hi> Crying out the word of the Lord, and the Lord ſaith, when the Lord hath not ſent them, nor ſpoken by them, they knowing not his voyce, neither have they ſeen his ſhape at any time, who is full of grace and truth; but feed people with imaginations in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping a God a far off ignorantly, when indeed <hi>our God is</hi> (not onely a God a far off, but) <hi>nigh</hi> at hand, <hi>and that which may be known of him, is manifeſt in man.</hi> But here is the <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> from the beginning, that <hi>man</hi> is <hi>not content with his Lot,</hi> and gift that God hath given him, but through luſt <hi>covets after, and eats of the forbidden fruit,</hi> which brings death upon his ſoul, and miſery and diſorder upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99439:7"/>the Creation, and from thence comes wars and fightings, rents and diviſions, even becauſe men abide <hi>not in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Gods Spirit,</hi> given to every man to profit withal, but run out in their vain minds to follow their own hearts luſts, and ſo ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked againſt the juſt; And many are aſhamed through the Croſs to return, by which the enmity comes to be deſtroyed, but go on untill their hearts are hardened unto deſtruction; that <hi>they</hi> themſelves ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding not in that wherein God makes people free to ſerve and worſhip him, but having loſt the way, and their wiſdoms confounded, they ſtrive alſo to keep others with themſelves ſtill in bondage, <hi>and even envy others in whom the power and Spirit of the Lord God is made manifeſt,</hi> which commeth not in their way, nor by obſervations, but <hi>worketh in us freely both to will, and to do, according to the good pleaſure of our Heavenly Father,</hi> which is contrary to the will and wiſdom of the fleſh, which pleaſeth not God; And let not the Spirit of bondage ſo prevaile in you any longer, to envy the Spirit of propheſy in Gods people, but <hi>come up to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty enemy of your Souls,</hi> and give up all the materialls of your own buildings unto the fire of the Lord, that your <hi>work</hi> may be <hi>tryed,</hi> that your hearts may be <hi>purified,</hi> and that <hi>you</hi> may be <hi>ſaved,</hi> ſo as by fire, for the <hi>Spirit of Judgment and burning muſt paſſe upon you,</hi> before ever your bodies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Temples of the holy Spirit, and you become veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of honour, fit for the Maſters uſe.</p>
            <p>I ſay again, and lay it upon you, that you expect not Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from the Hills, nor from the Moutains, <hi>But wait in the Light,</hi> for the coming of the <hi>Holy One</hi> in <hi>Gods own-way,</hi> and the Reſurrection of the <hi>Juſt</hi> out of the grave, where he <hi>lyes buried</hi> in <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> ſpiritually (ſo called) <hi>under your luſts</hi> and corruptions which war againſt your Soules, that you may know him, <hi>the word nigh in the heart,</hi> and in the mouth, who is <hi>ready to helpe,</hi> and <hi>mighty to ſave;</hi> and that you may come to feel the <hi>Seed</hi> of Gods Kingdom <hi>in your own hearts,</hi> working out the ſeed of corruption, and all that worketh abomination, and whatſoever loveth and maketh a lye, which is for the lake of fire, into which the Beaſt and falſe prophet is to be taken
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99439:8"/>and caſt a live; That you may know the <hi>children of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> begotten of the ſeed of the bond-woman <hi>caſt out,</hi> that the right Heir and Seed may take his Poſſeſſion, and Inherit the Kingdom, whoſe right it is to reign in the kingdoms of men; and bleſſed are they that are become joynt heirs with him of that Inheritance which is everlaſting, and never ſhall fade away. And thus Friends, as from the Lord, well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>you are not, as you ſtand in the way of Gods Salvation,</hi> have I written in the uprightneſſe of my heart, and in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der love to your ſouls, and to that pure ſeed which yet breaths in ſome of you after the living God, that you may yet at length be turned from darkneſſe to the Light, that ſo you may be brought from under Satans power into the power of God, that you may no longer lye under that <hi>Yoak and ſpirit of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> which by <hi>your leaders</hi> is begotten amongſt you, and laid upon your Conſciences to keep <hi>you from the Covenant of Light and Life,</hi> but that you might come forth in the freedom of the Lords Spirit, out of the houſe of Bondage, into the liberty of the Sons of God, in newneſs of ſpirit, to worſhip and ſerve him all the dayes of your life.</p>
            <p>It's a ſtrange doctrine, that you muſt believe as your Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers believe, and do what they do, as infallible; whilſt they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves know not, but deny the immediate or preſent teachings of <hi>Gods infallible Spirit</hi> amongſt them, and come not to feel and know in your ſelves the <hi>true Teachers</hi> the <hi>living Hope,</hi> and the <hi>true Faith</hi> of Gods Elect which <hi>purifyeth the heart,</hi> which God requires, even truth in the inwards parts; what are your Teachers more than others of the world, that you ſhould be ſo in bondage to them, as to fear their threats of death and deſtruction, or the like of that (whileſt they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are under the power thereof) to whomſoever ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from them, and turn from their pernitious wayes? That many poor ſouls that have entred themſelves in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as it were with death, under their beggarly and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Rudiments, are affraid of their big-ſwelling words and excommunications to come our from amongſt them, and becauſe of the <hi>Flood that proceeds out of the Dragons mouth againſt the woman that travells to bring forth the man Child</hi> that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99439:8"/>ſhall Rule the Nations, you come not up to the war of the Lamb: Though you may ſee and believe in your Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that there is a more excellent and living way known and ſet before you, and are not ſatisfied with that food which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth, but groan in your ſpirits for the bread of life: And were it not for fear of perſecution which follows the righteous Seed, and the ſhame of the Croſs on the one hand, and the fear of your Teachers on the other hand, would you not come out from amongſt them? Deal faithfully with your own ſouls, and Gods witneſſe in you, and confeſſe the truth to Gods Glory, and come away out of all that's dead and carnal, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the living truth of our God.</p>
            <p>For truly Friends, this I verily believe, as <hi>Gods witneſſe</hi> comes <hi>again</hi> to be <hi>raiſed in you,</hi> in whom he is not yet ſlain, (as ſome have done by warring againſt him) that there will not be a time of diſputing and halting left you, but you muſt either come away to follow <hi>the Lamb, the Light of the world,</hi> or take your portion in that lake that burns with fire and brimſtone, where you ſhall know that worm that never dies, &amp; that fire that never ſhall be quenched; and there ſhall not be peace again (ſaith my God) to the wicked, but torment day and night, diſtraction, horror and confuſion, ſhall be their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that comes not out of <hi>Babylon</hi> at Gods Call, which hath reached unto you: therefore haſten to come away, and follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goes, that with him you may reign in glory on Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> for ever and ever. And whether you hear, or forbear; whether ye believe, or not; this again I tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay and teſtify, that in bowels of tender love to your pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſouls and the ſeed of God, in diſcharge of my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards God and you, that I may ſtand clear of your blood, have I written; knowing that the day of the Lord haſtens, wherein he will render to every man according to his deeds done in the body, whether they be good or evil, when many ſhall cry and call to the Rocks and to the Mountains to fall upon them and cover them; But in that day <hi>none of your Coverings,</hi> but the Covering of the Lords Spirit <hi>ſhall hide you</hi> from the wrath of the Lamb. And you ſhall certainly know, that I ſpeak the truth in Chriſt Jeſus, and lye not.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Bridgwater</hi> 
                  <date>the 10th of the 5th month, 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>John Anderdon</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
